331
Grand Central Terminal, Park Avenue, New York is the world's
largest railway station
highest railway station
longest railway station
None of the above
1	
Entomology is the science that studies
Behavior of human beings
Insects
The origin and history of technical and scientific terms
The formation of rocks
2	
Eritrea, which became the 182nd member of the UN in 1993, is in the continent of
Asia
Africa
Europe
Australia
2	
Garampani sanctuary is located at
Junagarh, Gujarat
Diphu, Assam
Kohima, Nagaland
Gangtok, Sikkim
2	
For which of the following disciplines is Nobel Prize awarded?
Physics and Chemistry
Physiology or Medicine
Literature, Peace and Economics
All of the above
4 	
Hitler party which came into power in 1933 is known as
Labour Party
Nazi Party
Ku-Klux-Klan
Democratic Party
2
In which year of First World War Germany declared war on Russia and France?
1914
1915
1916
1917
1	
ICAO stands for
International Civil Aviation Organization
Indian Corporation of Agriculture Organization
Institute of Company of Accounts Organization
None of the above
1	
India's first Technicolor film ____ in the early 1950s was produced by ____
'Jhansi Ki Rani', Sohrab Modi
'Jhansi Ki Rani', Sir Syed Ahmed
'Mirza Ghalib', Sohrab Modi
'Mirza Ghalib', Munshi Premchand
1	
India has largest deposits of ____ in the world.
gold
copper
mica
None of the above
3	
How many Lok Sabha seats belong to Rajasthan?
32
25
30
17
2 	
Kiran Bedi received Magsaysay Award for government service in
1992
1993
1994
1995
3 	
Logarithm tables were invented by
John Napier
John Doe
John Harrison
John Douglas
1 	
With which sport is the Jules Rimet trophy associated?
Basketball
Football
Hockey
Golf
2 	
Joule is the unit of
temperature
pressure
energy
heat
3	
Kemal Ataturk was
the first President of Independent Kenya
the founder of modern Turkey
revolutionary leader of Soviet Union
None of the above
2 	
Milkha Singh Stood ____ in 1960 Olympics, in Athletics.
fourth in 400m final
second in 400m final
eighth in 50km walk
seventh in 800m final
1	
Squadron leader Rakesh Sharma was India's first man to go into space. He was ____ cosmonaut to be in space in the world.
12th
107th
139th
151st
3	
Philology is the
study of bones
study of muscles
study of architecture
science of languages
4	
The 2006 World Cup Football Tournament held in
France
China
Germany
Brazil
3	
Satellite launching station is located at
Sriharikotta (Andhra Pradesh)
Solapur (Maharashtra)
Salem (Tamilnadu)
Warangal (Andhra Pradesh)
1	
The 'Black flag' signifies
revolution/danger
peace
protest
truce
3 	
Republican party is
One of the important parties in USA
the political parties which has no definite principles
the political party which changes with the change in the times and circumstances in the country
All of the above
4	
The chief constituent of gobar gas is
ethane
methane
hydrogen
carbon dioxide
2	
The countries that had maintained research stations in Antarctica under Antarctic Trade are
Argentina, Australia, Belgium and South Africa
Chili, France and Japan
New Zealand, Norway, the former USSR, the UK and the USA
All of the above
4	
The first development flight of SLV-3 took place on
May 31, 1981
April 17, 1983
December 21, 1999
December 28, 1995
1	
The Enron project is a
hydro-electric project
thermal power project
atomic power project
gas-fired power project
4 	
The chief purpose of crop rotation is to check the loss of top soil
by water erosion
by wind erosion
by weathering
of its mineral content
4	
World's busiest airports by passenger traffic is
Hartsfield-Jackson Atlanta International Airport, USA
Lhasa Airport, Tibet
King Abdul Aziz International Airport, Saudi Arabia
Chicago O' Hare International Airport, USA
1	
The main objectives of the UN are
to maintain peace and security in the world
to work together to remove poverty, disease and illiteracy and encourage respect for each other's rights of basic freedom.
to develop friendly relations among nations
All of the above
4 	
The headquarter of ESCAP Economic and Social Commission for Asia are situated at
Bangkok
Geneva
Santiago (Chile)
Baghdad
1	
The industrial organization of Atomic Minerals Division, Heavy Water Board (HWB) is located at
Mumbai
Kolkata
Hyderabad
Jadugude, Bihar
1	
The Indian Air Force celebrated its Golden Jubilee in
1962
1972
1982
1992
3	
The headquarter of OAU (Organization of African Unity) are at
Addis Ababa, Ethiopia
Washington DC
Paris
Jakarta, Indonesia
1	
The headquarter of International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA) are situated at
Vienna
Geneva
Rome
Paris
1	
The Olympic Flame, was, for the first time, ceremonially lighted and burnt in a giant torch at the entrance of the stadium at
Athens Games (1896)
London Games (1908)
Paris Games (1924)
Amsterdam Games (1928)
4	
The Olympic Flame symbolises
unity among various nations of the world
speed, perfection and strength
sports as a means for securing harmony among nations
continuity between the ancient and modern games
4	
The reaction which converts sugar solution into alcohol is an example of
saponification
hydrogenation
fermentation
hydrolysis
3 	
The Scottish bacteriologist who discovered penicillin was
Alexander Fleming
Albert Einstein
Archimeder
Aryabhatta
1	
The number of already named bones in the human skeleton is
200
206
212
218
2	
The purpose of United Nations Fund for Population Activities (UNFPA) is
studying population dynamics
collecting population data
evolving population policies, family planning and related programmes
All of the above
4	
UN General Assembly elects a President and how many Vice Presidents at the start of its each regular session?
Seven
Fifteen
Twenty one
Two
3 	
The treaty which ushered in NATO, was signed by the member nations at
Geneva
London
Paris
Washington
4	
The unit of current is
ohm
watt
ampere
None of the above
3	
Thomas Cup is associated with
badminton
billiards
lawn tennis
table tennis
1	
Theory of Idealism was expounded by George Hegal, Bishop George and Berkeley According to this
mathli is an illusion and that the only reality that which exists mentally
good was pleasure and that evil was pain
base of knowledge is sense-experience, that is, observations governed by scientific principles
all knowledge is derived from sensory experience, by observing and experimenting
1	
To which country does the present UN Secretary-General belongs?
Ghana
South Korea
Spain
Sweden
2	
When light passes from air into glass it experiences change of
frequency and wavelength
frequency and speed
wavelength and speed
frequency, wavelength and speed
3	
When is the World's Diabetes Day?
14th November
11th December
15th October
1st July
1 	
When did Margaret Thatcher became the first women Prime Minister of Britain?
1998
1989
1979
1800
3	
When is the International Workers' Day?
15th April
12th December
1st May
1st August
3	
What is the population density of Madhya Pradesh?
202/sq. km
196/sq. km
116/sq. km
68/sq. km
2	
When a moving bus stops suddenly, the passenger are pushed forward because of the
friction between the earth and the bus
friction between the passengers and the earth
inertia of the passengers
inertia of the bus
3	
Which countries from the membership of CACM (Central American Common Market)?
Costa Rica, EI Salvador, Guatemala, Honduras, Nicaragua
Bogota, EI Salvedor, Honduras
Washington DC, Bogota, Guatemala
All of the above
1	
Which company manufacturers low and high power communication equipment like radius for the use of defence services and paramilitary organisations?
Bharat Electronics Limited (BEL)
God Shipyard Limited (GSL)
Bharat Dynamic Limited (BDL)
None of the above
1 	