361
Ordinary table salt is sodium chloride. What is baking soda?
Potassium chloride
Potassium carbonate
Potassium hydroxide
Sodium bicarbonate
4	
Ozone hole refers to
hole in ozone layer
decrease in the ozone layer in troposphere
decrease in thickness of ozone layer in stratosphere
increase in the thickness of ozone layer in troposphere
3	
Pine, fir, spruce, cedar, larch and cypress are the famous timber-yielding plants of which several also occur widely in the hilly regions of India. All these belong to
angiosperms
gymnosperms
monocotyledons
dicotyledons
2 	
Pollination is best defined as
transfer of pollen from anther to stigma
germination of pollen grains
growth of pollen tube in ovule
visiting flowers by insects
1	
Plants receive their nutrients mainly from
chlorophyll
atmosphere
light
soil
4	
Movement of cell against concentration gradient is called
osmosis
active transport
diffusion
passive transport
2	
Photosynthesis generally takes place in which parts of the plant?
Leaf and other chloroplast bearing parts
stem and leaf
Roots and chloroplast bearing parts
Bark and leaf
1	
Most fish do not sink in water because of the presence of: I.swim bladder, II.air bladder, III.air sacs, IV.air in spongy bones.
I and II are correct
II and III are correct
III and IV are correct
I, II, III and IV are correct
1	
Plants synthesis protein from
starch
sugar
amino acids
fatty acids
3	
Plants absorb dissolved nitrates from soil and convert them into
free nitrogen
urea
ammonia
proteins
1 	
Out of 900 reported species of living gymnosperms, conifers are represented by about 500 species, About 2,50,000 species of angiosperms (flowering plants) have also been reported in the world. The vast and dominant woodlands in Europe, Asia, North America and mountains such as Himalayas are wooded with
all gymnosperms, except conifers
only angiosperms
only conifers
angiosperms and all gymnosperms except conifers
3 	
One of the following is not a function of bones.
Place for muscle attachment
Protection of vital organs
Secretion of hormones for calcium regulation in blood and bones
Production of blood corpuscles
3	
Plants absorb most part of water needed by them through their
embryonic zone
growing point
root hairs
zone of elongation
3 	
Photo-oxidation is
photorespiration
photolysis
light and oxygen induced breakdown
All of the above
4	
Process of cell division can take place by
heterosis
fusion
mitosis
None of these
3	
Most highly intelligent mammals are
whales
dolphins
elephants
kangaroos
2	
Plant development is influenced by
quality of light only
quality and quantity of light
quality and duration of light
quality, quantity and duration of light
4	
Prokaryotic cells lack
nucleolus
nuclear membrane
membrane bound by organelles
All of these
4
Photosynthesis takes place faster in
yellow light
white light
red light
darkness
2	
Nucleus, the genetic material containing rounded body in each cell, was first discovered in 1831 by
Robert Hooke
Robert Brown
Rudolf Virchow
Theodore Schwann
2	
Primary phloem develops from
lateral meristem
protoderm
extrastelar cambium
provascular tissue
4 	
Other than spreading malaria, anopheles mosquitoes are also vectors of
dengue fever
filariasis
encephalitis
yellow fever
2 	
Plants that grow in saline water are called
halophytes
hydrophytes
mesophytes
thallophytes
1	
Pyorrhoea is a disease of the
nose
gums
heart
lungs
2	
O2 released in the process of photosynthesis comes from
CO2
water
sugar
pyruvic acid
2 	
Placenta is the structure formed
by the union of foetal and uterine tissue
by foetus only
by fusion of germ layers
None of these
1	
Plants hormone that induces cell division is
auxins
gibberellins
kinins
domins
3	
Neurospora is used as genetic material because
it has short life cycle of 10 days
the product of single meiosis can be easily analysed
meiotic products are linearly arranged in the form of ordered tetrads
is a diploid fungus
1	
Phloem is a tissue found in
reproductive organs of animals
plants
insects
mammals
2 	
N2 content is kept constant in the biosphere due to
N2 fixation
industrial pollution
nitrogen cycle
absorption of N2
3 	
out of proteins, lipids and carbohydrates present in a cell membrane, what is true?
Lipids are maximum
Carbohydrates are minimum
Carbohydrates are maximum
All three are in equal proportion
2 	
Potato is a modified form (outgrowth) of
root
stem
fruit
leaf
2	
Of the following taxonomic categories which is the most inclusive (i.e. is the highest in hierarchy)?
Order
Subspecies
Class
Genus
3	
Prothrombin which helps in clotting of blood is released by
lymphocytes
erythrocytes
monocytes
blood platelets
4 	
Myopia is connected with
ears
eyes
lungs
None of these
2	
Most of the red, blue and purple colours of plants are due to a pigment called
anthocyanin
carotene
chlorophyll
xanthophylls
1	
Plants developing in dry conditions are
xerophytes
mesophytes
lithophytes
hydrophytes
1 	
Plants growing on sand are called as
chasmophytes
oxylophytes
lithophytes
psammophytes
4 	
Our skin, when exposed to excess sunlight, becomes dark. This is because our skin pigments called
flavoxanthin
melanin
carotene
Xanthophyll
2 	
Ramapithecus and Cro-Magnon man are considered
ancestors of modern man
ancestors of monkey
ancestors of lion
None of the above
1 	
Normal adult human male has
10 gram of haemoglobin/100 gram of blood
14 gram of haemoglobin/100 gram of blood
18 gram of haemoglobin/100 gram of blood
24 gram of haemoglobin/100 gram of blood
2 	
Plants wilt due to excess of
transpiration
photosynthesis
absorption
None of these
1	
Monotremes are unique mammals because they
posses hair
give birth to live young
secret milk in a pouch
lay eggs
4	
Poison glands of snakes are homologous to
electric organs of fishes
stings of rays
sebaceous glands of mammals
salivary glands of vertebrates
4 	
Radical vascular bundles are those in which
xylem is surrounded by phloem
phloem is surrounded by xylem
xylem and phloem occur on the same radius
xylem and phloem occur on the different radii
4	
Plant bends towards the source of light on account of the movement of curvature known as
geotropism
thigmotropism
chemotropism
phototropism
4 	
Plant have ____ while animals lack it.
starch
cellulose
protein
fat
2 	
Osmosis is the flow of solution from higher concentration to a solution of lower concentration through a semi permeable membrane. What is incorrect in this statement?
Exact concentration of solution is not given
Character of semi permeable membrane is not given
The flow of solution is not possible through semi permeable membrane
All are incorrect
3 	
Photosynthesis is a process
reductive and exergonic
reductive and catabolic
reductive, endergonic and catabolic
reductive, endergonic and anabolic
4	
On which of the following plants did Gregor Mendal perform his classical experiment?
Gram
Maize
Pea
Wheat
3 	
Pigmentation of skin is due to
lymphocytes
monocytes
leucocytes
melanocytes
4	
Norepinephrine increases
respiration
urine production
saliva production
blood pressure
4	
Night blindness is cause by lack of which vitamin?
Vitamin A
Vitamin B
Vitamin C
Vitamin D
1 	
Monocot root differs from dicot root in having
open vascular bundles
scattered vascular bundles
well developed pith
radially arranged vascular bundles
3	
Radioactivity is a phenomenon of the spontaneous emission of
protons (alpha particles)
electrons (beta particles)
gamma rays (short wave electromagnetic waves)
All of the above
4	
Organic Substances which, in very small amounts, control growth and development called
vitamins
hormones
enzymes
None of the above
2 	
Our major foods, fibres, spices, fruits and beverage crops are
flowering plants
gymnosperms plants
pteridophytes
bryophytes
1	
Movements due to light are shown by
flowering plants
lower plants
all land plants
all the plants
1	
Outer covering of virus made up of protein is
capsid
coat
virion
viriod
1	
Radish is a
bulb
conn
modified root
tuber
3